Hello, welcome everyone. It is February
25th, 2026. We are in Active Inference
guest stream 15.4 with Bobby Azerian and
guests Kevin Schmidt and Carl Fristen.
Looking forward to this presentation and
discussion. Bobby will present some
slides and then we will have a panel
discussion and I'll read some live
chats. So thank you to Bobby and guests
for joining and please take it away
Bobby
Prince Institute. I love talking to you
because uh this can be um technical and
accessible at the same time which I
think it really needs to be for this
topic. Uh and thank you to Kevin and
Carl for attending. Uh if you guys have
any questions or comments, just feel
free to jump in. Um there are about 60
slides, so I'm going to try to keep this
to under an hour. So I'm going to be
going through slides pretty quickly. Uh
and we will not get to some of the stuff
that I wanted to about how this informs
AI, but we'll touch on that at the end.
But we're going to focus on one of the
greatest mysteries of science. Uh the
mystery of consciousness. Uh it's it's
one of the the great uh remaining
mysteries of science. Um so the
framework that we're going to use to try
to answer this mystery is called strange
loop theory. And uh I named it that
after Douglas Hoffstatter's
strange loop idea that he wrote about in
his Pulitzer Prizewinning book Golden Go
to Usherbach and again in the follow-up
I am a strange loop. Um bringing that
idea together with uh major neuroscience
theories and consciousness theories
specifically uh Carl's free energy
principle and Tenon's integrated
information theory. Uh so yeah let's
begin.
So Richard Fineman
uh had this famous statement what I
cannot create I do not understand more
commonly spoken as if if you if you
can't uh build it you don't understand
it. So this was written on the
blackboard during the time of his death
and will serve as a kind of theme for
this talk. So the converse is also true.
If we can build it, then we understand
it at least to some degree. So building
a conscious machine would be the
ultimate test of any theory of
consciousness. Maybe the term machine
isn't perfect because for example, if we
create AI on self-organized neuromorphic
hardware, for example, there are these
silver nanowire networks that uh
self-organized and do we call that a
machine? It's more like life. Let's
let's say building a conscious AI system
is the ultimate test of any theory of
consciousness. And let's call that
Fineman's challenge. We claim to
understand consciousness. Uh I I think
we that's that's the the big claim of
this talk is that we understand the
mechanisms enough to say that in theory
we understand what gives rise to
consciousness and we want to prove that
ultimately by building a a conscious
system.
So
um what this presentation offers a
mechanistic explanation of how
consciousness arises from physical
processes. Uh it's also going to briefly
give a cosmic explanation for why
consciousness exists which is more of a
philosophical and existential claim. uh
and we will briefly touch on an engine
an engineering path to prove our model
uh by designing
uh a conscious system.
So we start with the infinite infamous
hard problem. David Chmer's defined this
problem explicitly in uh 1995, but it's
a it's a problem that's really centuries
old. It's kind of a restatement of the
mind body problem. So what is
consciousness and why does it exist?
Before we can explain consciousness, we
need to define it. That's always been a
tricky issue. Um because
for example, you can have an AI system,
an LLM that responds as if it's uh
conscious, but we have no good reason to
believe that these systems actually have
phenomenal experience. So it gets real
tricky when you're trying to give a
scientific uh description or definition
of consciousness. The philosopher Thomas
Nagel
uh posed a solution just basically
defining consciousness as uh something
it is like to be um a conscious entity.
So an organism that has conscious uh an
organism has conscious mental states
if and only if there's something it is
like to be that organism. He has a
famous essay what is it like to be a
bat?
So to understand anything it's best to
understand its opposite to to compare it
to something else. Um so when David
Chmer's outlined the hard problem he
also outlined the easy problem and the
easy problem which isn't easy at all.
It's extremely hard but it seemed
tractable because in the '9s uh
functional uh MRI was getting popular
and these new neuroiming tools were
being used in conjunction with uh
cognitive psychology
uh measures and we were basically you
know understanding the cognitive
mechanisms associated with
consciousness. So the easy problem is a
series of problems that include
understanding perception. So how we
discriminate and categorize stimuli
attention. So what we attend to is what
we're conscious of. So to understand
consciousness, we really need to
understand how attention works. Um
integration
uh how we bind sensory processing ste uh
streams. There's this famous binding
problem. uh how how is our visual and
our auditory
um streams of information uh bound
together into a a coherent hole and the
difference between sleep and awake
states and states under anesthesia. So
consciousness is something that emerges
when we awake and then leave. So there's
something there's a phenomenon there
that needs to be explained. Um the hard
problem
is not about those cognitive mechanisms.
It's about why is physical information
processing why is does it have a
feeling? Why is there subjective
experience accompanying
uh this cognition? So we know our
computers do uh complex information
processing tasks but we don't think that
uh our computers um that there's
anything it's like to be our computer.
So there seems to be this explanatory
gap. How do we get from mechanism to
experience? And that that's really the
hard problem. It's the mystery of
subjective experience.
So I think we have things backwards. I
think the hard problem is the easy
problem not not necessarily easy but the
easier problem. Uh you can answer the
hard problem with a theoretical
explanation where the easy problem is
this set of super hard um
you know it's a technical problem where
we have to understand the no nuts and
bolts of uh the cognitive processes that
are associated with consciousness. Um so
I think the easy problem um
will still remain a problem um after the
hard problem is pretty much solved. And
actually by the end of this talk we can
maybe see that this distinction is kind
of meaningless that there's just one
problem and that when you understand the
hard problem uh you it becomes an
additional problem on top of the other
uh easy problem. So we need to
understand perception, attention,
integration and also uh world and
self-modeling. And when we add
self-modeling to that list of uh easy
problems, then we start to get at the
mechanism underlying the generation of
conscious experience.
So
um once we explain how a self emerges
through mechanism and understand what
qualia are in these terms what remains
is a challenge not a problem. So it's
kind of an optimistic spin on this. So
today the goal is to convert the hard
problem into a hard challenge and that's
um what we call the super hard problem.
So how can we create a conscious system
from scratch? This requires solving both
the hard and easy problems sufficient uh
to reproduce the phenomenon. So this is
Fineman's challenge applied to
consciousness and the claim is that
strange loop theory converts the hard
problem into an engineering
specification. Build a system with an
integrated model of the world then have
that system model itself modeling the
world.
So uh if we want to address this
problem, we should talk about the
philosophical landscape, the uh
different existing positions on
consciousness so we can see what they
get right and what they potentially get
wrong. Um and when we talk about these
different stances on consciousness,
we're going to be talking about
philosophies like materialism, idealism,
dualism, pansychism. Um these uh are
stances that address what could be
called the hard problem of reality. So
so what's the nature of existence? Is it
all physical? Is it all mental? Is it a
combination of the two? If so, how do
those things interact? So to solve one,
we must solve the other it seems.
So dualism uh that was the early stance
uh famous one uh by Deart uh who had the
famous statement uh I think therefore I
am. So Deart uh basically said that
reality consists of two distinct
substances. There's this material stuff
and then there's this mental stuff. Um
and somehow minds influence matter. But
he didn't really explain how this uh
influence happens which leads to a a
ghost in the machine problem where you
have something that is seemingly
immaterial pushing material stuff around
and that seems to violate the
mechanistic worldview of science, the
Newtonian worldview. Um Deart was a
Christian so he equated consciousness
with the soul and for that reason
dualism has pretty much um uh fallen out
of popularity with modern um scientists
and philosophers except in a weaker form
which is called property dualism. And
this says there's only one substance but
some systems can have non-physical
properties like consciousness which have
genuine causal power over their material
components. And so uh Chomemer himself
and Kristoff Ko are sympathetic to this
stance and uh there may be nothing wrong
with this stance. This may you know
basically it's saying that the mental
emerges from the material and it also
has causal power. So um like the other
ones we're going to see when someone
asks is dualism right? You have to ask
what do you mean by dualism exactly? So
materialism
um pretty much replaced uh dualism in
academia in the 19th and 20th centuries.
Uh this was called eliminative
reductionism. Um because scientists had
this physical and mechanistic worldview.
U they weren't sure how to handle
consciousness and subjective experience.
So the the the sort of move the chess
move they made was to completely um
ignore consciousness or say that
consciousness doesn't exist in the sense
that we think it does and that kind of
magically got rid of the problem. So
that was called eliminative eliminative
reductionism.
It was popular with um the church lens.
Um, this led to the illusionist position
that just set it out right that
consciousness isn't real, it's an
illusion. Um, made popular by people
like Daniel Dennett and Keith Frankish
and basically says consciousness emerges
from neural activity, but phenomenal
experience is a cognitive mirage. So,
this kind of just evaporates the hard
problem. But the paradox is they're
saying it's an emergent property, but
that it doesn't exist at the same time.
So, which one is it? Um, illusionists
live life as if consciousness is real
and has causal power. So, it's you
you're kind of like a walking
contradiction. If you're an illusionist,
um, and you can't get away from this uh
simple kito erosum statement of Decart,
I think, therefore I exist. So, denying
the subjective means denying the reality
of the map you're navigating with. Um
Dan Dennit's book consciousness
explained is jokingly called
consciousness ignored by uh
consciousness researchers because uh
rather than addressing the issue of
experience head-on, it just kind of
dodges it. And John Surl said that when
it comes to consciousness, the illusion
is the reality. So we know
consciousness, we know the map is not
the territory. It's uh virtual
construction and Neil Seth calls it a
hallucination. But that's something
calling it not real, saying it doesn't
exist doesn't make sense because the
virtual simulation that that model
that's something itself. So you can't
really say it's an illusion. An illusion
to who? The the the statement itself um
suggests uh an agent of experience.
So there's also idealism which says
everything emerges from consciousness.
The mind creates reality. The problem
with uh what you could call naive
idealism is that things exist that no
one has observed. If if an astronaut
goes to another planet and
uh doesn't see a rock
in his in his path and trips on that, he
he trips on something real that's never
been observed by anyone. So the idea
that the mind is creating reality has a
fundamental flaw unless
uh you are talking about a form of
idealism like analytic idealism.
um which basically says that the the
material world emerges from this uh
consciousness that's a universal
consciousness. That's a very different
um argument. And so is idealism right or
wrong? Well, it depends on what version
you're talking about. Um this framework
would say that fundamentally uh the
universe is uh an information processing
system. So if you see mind as
information processing then uh yes mind
is fundamental in that sense. Um but if
you're defining mind as what it's like
to be something then it seems that mind
emerges with life and probably you know
robustly with with brains not until
brains. Um pansychism is a similar idea.
It doesn't try to explain away the
material. It just says that um the
material world has this conscious aspect
to it and that everything whether you're
talking about you know atoms or chairs
or the universe as a whole is conscious
again if you're talking about
information processing then one could
make the claim that the universe is
conscious and that it's processing
information but if you're defining
consciousness like nagel what it's like
to be something um then I don't think
pansychism is right. I don't think Adams
I don't think there's anything it's like
to be an atom or a chair. Um but this
frameworks one could call it a sort of
emergent pansychism that that
consciousness inevitably emerges in the
universe and spreads as life spreads
outwards. So um
the last position that I'll mention is
mysterionism
uh made popular in the '9s by the
philosopher Colin McInn. Um
neuroscientist Eric Hull um holds this
position now in a kind of new version, a
kind of Godian version. That's
interesting. Um, just as a dog cannot
comprehend quantum mechanics, uh, humans
may lack the conceptual apparatus to
solve the hard problem. Um, and Eric
says consciousness may be fundamentally
undecidable
like a gold sentence. Um, our response
is that godellian slipperiness isn't a
roadblock, but the engine of discovery.
Um, understanding consciousness does
change the configuration of the
conscious system comprehending itself,
producing something emergent, something
new to understand.
Um, so yeah, in some way the the mystery
of consciousness will go on forever
because of this. Um, understanding
consciousness will create new
configurations in reality that need to
be understood. So it's kind of this um
godellian
uh problem that that that you have to
create these meta frameworks for. Um but
this creates an infinite ladder of
understanding that drives scientific
progress and knowledge creation. So the
mystery of consciousness
um is really an engine of progress. Um
and so uh when we're done with the
framework, we'll see how each position
represents a partial truth. Um and when
the mysteries unravel, they will be seen
as complimentary rather than
contradictory.
And so we will talk about a a third hard
problem. In addition to the hard problem
of consciousness and the hard problem of
reality, there's the practical hard
problem that we're all dealing with
every day. Uh we can call this the hard
problem of survival.
Um so this problem's not philosophical
like the others but practical yet it
provides the solution that solves all
our hard problems. The key is
understanding why minds exist in the
first place and that's to aid survival
to aid persistence.
So
uh minds uh exist um for a basic
thermodynamic reason for a thermodynamic
imperative.
So this has become famous uh to
scientists this uh saying I I don't
think it's known enough but the saying
is the second law of thermodynamics is
the first law of psychology
um that was made explicit in a paper in
2003.
So this idea is our mental processes
function to help us resist entropy's
pull. Minds are required for
persistence. To acquire energy and avoid
threats, which is what we need to do to
persist, we must model the world. And
this is uh pretty much what the free
energy principle uh and the basian brain
process are are are based on. This is
how they frame it. Um to resist entropy
uh agents have to create uh predictive
models.
So this is an old idea goes back all the
way to Irwin Schroinger. Uh the famous
physicist uh wrote a great book in 1944.
What is life? Actually based on a
lecture. So everyone should check that
out if they don't know it. It says
living systems seem to defy the disorder
and tendency associated with the second
law. Life creates and maintains islands
of remarkable organization not by
violating physics but by extracting
energy from the environment. So to stay
ordered you have to get energy. To get
energy, you have to build a model of the
world.
And Dennett said in 1995, "What then are
living things? There are things that
defy this crumbling into dust, at least
for a while, by not being isolated, by
taking in their environment, the
wherewithal to keep life and limb
together." So you see this recurring
theme in popular science books. In 2017,
Steven Pinker wrote, "The second law
defines the ultimate purpose of life,
mind, and human striving to deploy
energy and information to fight back the
tide of entropy and carve out refues of
beneficial order." So, we can really
understand purpose and agency through
this window. Uh, agency uh is basically
um this uh struggle to maintain
persistence in a world that tends toward
entropic decay. though Anneil Seth more
recently says I have to actively resist
the second law of thermodynamics so I
don't dissipate into all kinds of states
I don't just dissolve into mush on the
floor it's an active process
and so this is tied to biological agency
but also intimately tied to
consciousness itself uh in that article
uh anal argues that consciousness may be
nature's way of allowing its intelligent
creations to keep going to almost always
find a way
So
uh to to to this kind of summarizes how
we get from uh entropy to experience. So
this is this is the narrative. The
second law creates this pressure. Um
systems uh have to resist dissolution
and to do that uh requires finding
energy and anticipating threats. So
navigation and anticipation requires
predictive modeling. You have to build a
map of the world to be able to get
around in it. And prediction requires
simulating counterfactuals. So the
argument is that consciousness is this
simulation. It's the virtual world the
system runs to select actions. So your
your brain is a computational system
running
a world model. But where does the self
come from? the I and I think therefore I
am. It's not just enough to have a world
model. The simulation becomes conscious
when the simulator appears inside its
own simulation. This is the strange
loop.
So on to the next part. Uh you are a
strange loop. How self-modeling creates
the self. So the argument is that there
are two requirements for consciousness.
First a system that builds a world model
to navigate entropic challenges. Second,
a recursive leap where that system
incorporates itself into its own model.
When a model begins modeling itself,
modeling the world, pretty loopy. Uh
something remarkable happens. A self-re
referential loop generates a
perspective, a vantage point, an eye. So
that was the real mystery. Um and the
concept of a simulation doesn't quite
get you there because our computer
simulations, they there's there's
nothing it is like to be those situ uh
simulations. So we need something more
and that's self-modeling. Um
so Douglas Hoffadder
uh you know this isn't a new idea. This
goes back to 1979 and he really
described it in detail. Um
and so he he calls a strange loop. He
describes it as a level crossing
information pathway that folds in on
itself. Something like a mental mobious
strip.
So the idea is that without
self-modeling the generative model is a
cartisian theater with no one in the
audience. Um so the world simulation is
not sufficient. It must place the
simulator within the simulated world and
we get a picture of reality being
relational from this. Uh so Hoffadder
um has this cool little demonstration he
likes to mention. Think of what happens
when a TV c camera is pointed uh at the
screen so as to display the screen on
itself. A self- engulfing television.
When and only when such a loop arises uh
in a brain or any other substrate is a
person, a unique eye brought into being.
And here's a picture of this strange
loop. So this is a camera pointed at a
monitor and you see this emergent uh
fractal structure. uh Hoffadder claims
that the the self, the eye, um emerges
in an analogous way. And
so um
how does the self model emerge? Um
unlike uh organisms that just have uh
genes, organisms with brains are able to
record the consequences of the
organism's actions in real time. So, so
you need brains to be able to map the
immediate causal consequences of your
actions. And when you're doing that,
then you're building up a model of the
self. Um, so that builds up uh a model
of your behavioral routines and patterns
and this generative model transforms
into an experiential subject when that
happens. Um so the phenomenological
world emerges from uh recursive
processing
and this doesn't just explain the
emergence of consciousness. Uh it
explains the emergence of levels of
consciousness. So self-consciousness
emerges um from uh an even higher level
of recursive processing and the strange
loop spawns a new level of control. So
it's not just that you're getting these
higher levels of awareness with richer
recursive processing. The system is also
gaining more autonomy, more causal power
over the over the world. It's not this
input output machine any longer. It can
understand its own coding and it can
modify itself.
So you have these different levels. So
the first level, the system models the
world. You just get agentic behavior. um
probably uh a sort of zombie system with
no um subjective experience. When the
system models itself modeling the world
with brains, we get consciousness. When
the system models itself self-modeling,
you get self-consciousness and a higher
level emerges. When the system models
itself within a larger system of agents,
um at this higher point of reflection,
um that gives rise to metacognition and
all of the uh great functions that we uh
have thanks to our um evolved prefrontal
cortex.
So each level adds a new level of top-
down control. It's it's it's really
enabling uh greater levels of agency. So
the more self-reerentially rich the
loop, the more conscious the self. So
we're going to talk about integrated
information theory later and the idea is
that uh integrated information is
necessary but not sufficient. You have
to have this uh self-reference.
So Judea Pearl uh who's been really
influential on AI with his uh work in uh
basian networks and causal modeling uh
says uh that's consciousness. You have a
model of yourself. Where do you get this
model? You look at yourself as if you're
part of the environment. I have a
blueprint of myself. So at that level I
can modify things. This is what we mean
by free will. So he connects
consciousness to selfmodeling but he
also connects it to higher agency. that
was on the Lex Friedman podcast.
Um, and Carl wrote a wonderful essay for
uh, Eon. Uh, I recommend that everyone
reads that because it ties all these
ideas together seamlessly. Uh, he says,
"Anytime there's a deviation from the
attractor, this triggers flows of
thoughts, feelings, and movements that
eventually take you back to your cycle
of attracting familiar states." this
view. In this view, humans are little
more than strange loops as Douglas
Hoffadder puts it. So, this is getting
at more than just the um the
self-modeling loop. We are cybernetic
controllers at a fundamental level. We
use feedback loops to sustain ourselves
uh against this tide of entropic decay.
And this you can see he mentions
feelings here.
So this gives us a new perspective on
qualia. Uh qualia is not uh epic
phenomenal qualitative experiences are
actually uh adaptive instructions. So
they serve uh to guide the conscious
system towards um a stable state. So to
guide the conscious system towards a far
from equilibrium state of dynamic
equilibrium. I guess you could call it a
non-equilibrium equilibrium. Uh
basically an organism tries to maintain
itself in this attractor and a dynamical
attractor
uh is applied to life is a state of
homeostatic balance. So what is pain in
this model? It's a high free energy
signal indicating dangerous deviation.
And so that's why when you touch a hot
stove, you um pull your hand back
quickly. It triggers withdrawal
instructions where pleasant sensations
are low free energy signals and uh um
basically signal the organism to
maintain adaptive behaviors. Of course,
this can be deceptive when we get into
uh you know can lead to addiction. But
that's uh the point of it. It's
basically um um a signal to keep uh
dynamic equilibrium against this
tendency to uh dissolve. So qualia are
not epiphenomenal as the illusionist
position maintains they have a causal
function.
And so now that we have an understanding
of how the subjective perspective
emerges from self-modeling and the
function of qualia, let's talk about um
how we can potentially
uh quantify uh consciousness um which is
what integrated information theory tries
to do with their measure fi and the
argument here is that consciousness
grows richer with cognitive complexity
specifically with the number of
accessible states the system can access.
So this idea is called repertoire
entropy. We're talking about the uh
number of states a system can
experience. So the average number of
states the typical human could
experience is far richer than the
average number of states of a of a cat,
which is far richer than the average
number of states accessible to uh a
mouse. Um so this idea is based on the
law of requisite variety. So the great
cyberneticist Ross Ashby um wrote this
paper in the 50s. The law says to
survive an organism must have a
repertoire of cognitive states and
behavioral responses as large as the
number of different challenges presented
by its environment. So a cat hunting
mice must have as many responses as the
ways the mouse can evade it. A swordsman
must have as many blocks as his opponent
has attacks.
And humans who live in a complex social
and technological world, um we require
uh an even greater repertoire of
responses. So the more options a system
has to respond, the more effectively it
can control its situation.
So this thing that we're saying
correlates with degree of consciousness,
has an adaptive function. um more states
means uh greater ability to control an
unpredictable world. So Francis Hiligan
says since the variety of perturbations
a system can potentially be confronted
with is unlimited, we should always try
to maximize its internal variety so as
to be optimally prepared for any
foreseeable or unforeseeable
contingency. Um this idea is uh popping
up in different places um from
computational neuroscience to um physics
to AI. So Alex Wisner Gross at Harvard
says um has this concept of causal
entropic forcing um which says that
there's this drive to maximize future
freedom of action. So life is trying to
increase options. It's trying to avoid
trap states.
uh Daniel Palani computational
neuroscientist has this concept of
empowerment
which is an agent's capacity to
influence its future states his
co-author says empowerment means being
in a state where you have the greatest
potential influence so very similar to
causal entropic forcing
um and empowerment is proportional to
requisite variety um why is this all
relevant to consciousness the size of
the mental repertoire relates directly
to the richness of experience and we're
going to explain why. Um,
so it's worth quickly mentioning the Red
Queen principle is a principle from
evolutionary theory that says as
competitors evolve, organisms must
expand their repertoire to stay viable.
So this fuels evolutionary arms races
which act as complexity ratchets. What
begins as simple molecular memory and
genomes eventually evolves into internal
representations in self-aware social
agents. So because of the need um to
complexify
uh life is always generating new species
that have um greater requisite variety.
And because the social world of modern
humans keeps growing more complex, uh,
evolution seems to be progressive.
There's always a new niche for
intelligence willing to take on more
complexity.
Kristoff Ko, uh, one of the famous
proponents of IIT says, the more complex
the system, the larger the repertoire of
conscious states it can experience. So,
this isn't some new obscure argument. Uh
this has been echoed by the leaders in
the field Robin Cart Harris a
psychedelics researcher uh has the
entropic brain hypothesis and he says
the view taken here is that the human
brain exhibits greater entropy than
other members of the animal kingdom
which is equivalent to saying the human
mind possesses a greater repertoire of
potential mental states than lower
animals.
So what does this mean? It means we can
potentially measure the information
content of a given observation.
And we can basically infer that um
observation
uh basically works in this uh same way
as observing um an outcome with like a
roll of of dice for example. Um so
when you uh toss a coin and you observe
the outcome, you get one bit of
information. Uh when you observe a
six-sided die toss outcome, you get 2.6
bits of information. So the amount of
information
um scales with the number of
possibilities.
And so that's a basic way um that's a
basic principle from Claude Shanton's
information theory. And so applying that
to consciousness we are saying that the
more possible states a cognitive system
can be in the higher the repertoire
entropy. So here entropy is not
measuring disorder but cognitive
bandwidth. Information is a reduction in
uncertainty. So the amount of
information in a signal is the
uncertainty reduced upon observation.
So that leads to the conclusion that the
depth of a conscious moment scales with
the number of states that could be
experienced but are not currently
actualized. Repertoire entropy measures
this richness. The greater the space of
possibilities, the more information in
an experience.
So the current experience would be
defined by the counterfactual cloud that
surrounds it. Red's redness emerges from
its position within contrast networks
relationships to green, blue, yellow,
and the entire perceivable spectrum.
And so we can imagine the simplest
organism, for example, a bacterium
performing chemotaxis. It basically only
has two states. If it senses chemical
food, it doesn't move. It doesn't do
anything. And then it basically sits and
feeds on that food. If it doesn't sense
food, it wiggles its tail and that moves
it uh to some new location until it
senses food. So you can imagine a system
with just two states where each state is
defined only by not being the other. So
to understand this new picture, there's
there's this kind of dialectical
relationship between presence and
absence. So this binary agent uh
wouldn't be able to perceive color. the
two states couldn't be um red and blue
for example. Um that the complexity of
the experience of color has to emerge
from this network of relationships.
Uh a system that can only experience two
states would only experience something
like light and dark. And it might even
be misleading to talk about a visual
modality because you don't have the
complexity for for different sensory
streams. It's really just presence or
absence. So if a sentient being were
confine confined to a binary repertoire
or a very small um number of accessible
states, then it wouldn't be able to have
quality in any meaningful sense. So it's
the spectrum of possible experiences we
could have but aren't having that makes
the present what it is. The more
accessible states, the greater the
variety of qualia.
So as we evolve and learn more and our
spectrum of possible experience
increases, so should the intensity with
with wi with which we feel them. The
information content of a conscious
experience increases in proportion to
the size of our mental repertoire. So
that's pretty interesting. It means as
we learn and as we go through life and
travel to different destinations, we're
basically unlocking more accessible
states. We're increasing the size of our
uh cognitive repertoire, our requisite
variety. And this makes me think
differently about everything. Like when
when I'm trying like new food, I'm I'm
seeing that as unlocking like new
quality and new states. And by doing
that and expanding the size of my uh
cognitive repertoire, um I should be
increasing the richness of each
conscious experience because each
observation will then be ruling out all
of the experiences that I could have had
but aren't having at that moment. So
it's it's it's a practical philosophy as
well. Uh repertoire entropy measures the
number of adaptive responses available.
So the requisite variety this has been
estimated in a paper by a cognitive
scientist named Denko Nikolic. Um so you
can actually uh kind of uh calculate
exact um
uh repertoire entropy figures for
different species based on what we know.
Um integrate information theories fi uh
touted as a measure for consciousness
um already captures this. Fi is
measuring the degree to which a system
is more than the sum of its parts. So
it's measuring emergence. Uh to
calculate fi you have to calculate uh
the repertoire entropy. It's it's
implicit in that calculation and fi is
constrained by repertoire size. So the
larger the repertoire, the larger the
potential fi. So the conclusion is fi is
a good proxy measure for consciousness
because it captures repertoire entropy.
But it should be emphasized that
integrated information is necessary but
not sufficient in this framework. Uh so
strange loop theory says consciousness
requires self-modeling in addition to
integrated information.
So how does this new framework uh
resolve old paradoxes? So, we're going
to just focus on two. Um, but really
this framework seems to dissolve uh all
of the major um philosophy of mind
paradoxes that have you know any any
book on consciousness you read will will
go through these and I think it it
addresses these pretty nicely. Um, so
there's this famous uh zombie problem
that that that Chomemers and Dennit uh
talked about and really made famous. But
the idea is that you can imagine um a
being or a system physically identical
to you but with no inner experience. So
it behaves exactly like you. It talks,
responds, claims to be a conscious but
there's nothing it's like to be that
thing. All the information processing is
happening in the dark the way our
computer processes information but we
don't believe it has a subjective
perspective. You could imagine a zombie
that looks like you that's not having
that experience. And Chomemer's argues
that if zombies are conceivable,
consciousness can't be physical, that it
must transcend the physical. Um, so this
has been used to argue for dualism for
decades.
So how does this framework handle it?
It's the It's really interesting because
it says this zombie idea, it's kind of
misguided, but it's actually super
important to understanding um like our
current AI systems. So you could embody
an LLM like chat GPT in a robot that
looks like you and it could have similar
um behavior and it could report all
these things but just just the way we
interact with LLMs and sometimes they'll
report being conscious um or having
experiences.
Um you could build a robot an embodied
LLM
um that's an actual zombie. So according
to this theory
uh and it's really pulling from
integrated information theory here uh
that system would be an actual zombie
because it has a feed forward
architecture. There's not the feedback
loops that that do this self-modeling.
Uh therefore um zombies uh are a real
concept like embodied robots that don't
create a persistent world model and
don't selfmodel would be zombies. Uh the
mistake about this problem, the the
mistake about this thought experiment
though is that um if that system does
have a world model the way brains encode
world models and it models itself, then
you'll no longer have a zombie. You will
have um a self-aware system and that may
require neuromorphic hardware. You may
need integrated information at the level
of the physical substrate. But if you do
have that and you have world and
self-modeling, then you won't have a
zombie. So the thought experiment is
flawed. It leaves out self-modeling. It
leaves out the mechanism that creates
consciousness. And if you duplicate that
mechanism, then um you're going to have
a conscious system, not a zombie.
The last one that we'll talk about is
Mary the Colorblind scientist. So in
this uh thought experiment, there's this
neuroscientist named Mary. She knows
everything about color perception.
Um everything about the neural pathways
involved in processing color, everything
about the different, you know,
wavelengths of color. Um she she knows
the entire physical picture uh about
what leads to um the experience of color
based on mechanism but she herself um
cannot experience color. Um so in this
thought experiment she underos a
treatment uh that actually gives her the
ability to experience color and she
learns something new once she has the
experience of red. uh for example, she
um knows something that she didn't know
before based on all of that um third
person objective scientific knowledge.
So the argument that people like
Chomemers like to use is that again
there's something in addition to the
physical that is gained by experience
and in a sense that's right but you can
map that on to to mechanism as well.
Before treatment, Mary had complete um
you know computational knowledge of
experience but she lacked the access to
specific positions within the conceptual
structure. So her knowledge was like
having a detailed map without ever
occupying any loca uh a specific
location within that map. When Mary
gains color vision, she doesn't acquire
new factual knowledge. Rather, her
system undergoes structural
transformation. New dimensions become
accessible. She can now occupy positions
in information space that dialectically
relate to other colors. So basically
there is a new information geometry that
correlates with her new experience. You
could think of every experience as a
sort of unique information crystal. So
she uh that there's a different
functional um structure to that
experience that is enabled um by the
surgery. So it's not really uh uh giving
us you know dualism or anything that
transcends the mechanism. What's going
on is she's unlocking a new brain state
that unlocks a new experiential state.
So how does this framework bridge the
explanatory gap? It says uh mind emerges
from matter without violating physics
though the phenomenon of consciousness
extends physics.
um it's a it's a new higher level
emergent phenomenon with um
new causal dynamics. So we will have to
come up with new mathematics and new
frameworks like um causal calculus of
Judea Pearl and um the information
geometry of integrated information
theory to understand consciousness. So
consciousness doesn't violate physics
but it creates new physics. Uh
consciousness isn't a new substance in
the sense that Dick Hart thought uh but
it is a new pattern of causal activity
and consciousness does enable a system
to have increased causal power. So it's
actually functional. It's not
epiphenomenal.
Uh it's not separate from the universe
it's in. Consciousness is more like a
whirlpool shaping water without being
separate from it. Um consciousness is
not so much a thing as it is a process.
And so that gives us an understanding of
how subjective experience emerges
um from mechanism. So the the how of
consciousness. But some people might not
be satisfied. They might be asking uh
well why does consciousness exist at
all?
So for some people the hard problem will
require getting into a philosophical
explanation.
So
uh I'll briefly mention the unifying
theory of reality. It's the sort of
theory of everything based on the free
energy principle that was presented in
uh my first book, the romance of
reality. Um and that's yeah kind of
beyond the scope of this talk. I'd love
to come back and give her another talk
just on that. But it basically suggests
that consciousness isn't an anomaly in
an indifferent universe. Uh it says that
the universe is a learning system. It's
a a system that's doing hierarchical
basian inference. And in this view,
consciousness is an expression of an
inherent tendency toward complexity, a
natural outgrowth of the evolutionary
dynamics of a self-organizing cosmos. So
to get slightly spiritual, we'll say um
we'll quote Carl Sean who said we are a
way for the universe to know itself. Uh
I think we need to take that statement
seriously, maybe even more seriously
than he did. Uh the idea is that
um reality is waking up through
conscious agents like us. So uh Irwin
Schroinger uh would write this on the
board at the end of his lectures towards
the end of his life. Uh he called it the
second Schroinger equation. Jokingly
it's uh what's called the identity
doctrine from uh um Hinduism the
it says atman equals Brahman. And atman
is just a word for individual
consciousness where Brahman is the term
for the universe as a whole. So maybe
this cosmic intelligence or cosmic
consciousness. So what this means it's
basically a restatement of the the Sean
statement. It's means that the universe
evolves towards self-nowledge through
the minds it creates.
So um yeah that's the idea is that we
are a way for reality to wake up and uh
this framework has explained conscious
theoretically. We've situated it
cosmically. Now we have to prove it by
building it. Uh it's just a theory until
you can demonstrate uh a conscious
system.
So
to wrap up we will
talk about that a bit uh and draw some
conclusions.
So going from theory to AI architecture
strange loop theory identifies the
mechanism of consciousness for cursive
self-modeling. This trait uh translates
directly into an engineering
specification.
Um I will be uploading some of um this
uh a couple couple white papers with
this engineering plan to my road to
Omega Substack in the near future. Uh
but basically uh you can design an
architecture where a system has an
explicit self model that tracks its own
capabilities, limitations, knowledge
states and uncertainty
um and goals, reasoning processes and
behavioral patterns. So you create a
metacognitive system and uh an AI
architecture that that self-reflects.
Um so the system needs to model itself
modeling the world that needs to be in
the design. You have to have the strange
loop.
And so when I say we want to create a
conscious system, I want to be very
clear and careful about what that means.
And that gets into a distinction of two
kinds of consciousness that the
philosopher Ned Block um has made
popular. Um so there's access
consciousness. Uh when we talk about um
consciousness in these terms, we're
talking about the information that's
available globally for reasoning,
reporting, and behavioral control. Um
we're talking about uh metacognition.
The system knows what it knows and
doesn't know. and access consciousness
is observable from behavior. Um, and
we're saying that yeah, we can create an
architecture that uh expresses the
behavioral signatures of consciousness.
It may be more accurate to say it's
simulating consciousness than than being
actually conscious. Um, and it it's not
clear whether that distinction really
matters, but it may because the second
type of consciousness is phenomenal
consciousness and that gets at this um
issue of experience. So something it's
like to be that thing. Um there is
actually uh a perceptual world with uh
an agent that's experiencing it from its
unique perspective. And if this
framework is right, you can create a
system that has access consciousness
that self-models
without having phenomenal consciousness
because you can basically create this
self-modeling architecture on standard
non-neuromorphic hardware. So GPUs with
a vonoyman architecture and you could
potentially have a system that behaves
as if it's conscious but is not having
the phenomenal experience. And so if
this framework is right, you need
neuromorphic hardware to have the
conscious experience. Of course, you
could run you could put the AI
architecture onto this neuromorphic
hardware. Um
uh there's uh silver nanowire networks
that are actually self-organizing
systems that that
basically um organize themselves the way
uh organic brains do. And so that could
be a substrate for having both access
and phenomenal consciousness. So I do
believe it's possible to have an
artificial system that has a subjective
perspective but fortunately you can have
access consciousness without phenomenal
consciousness it seems. So if this is
the case then the architecture that we
have would be for building AGI without
the ethical weight of creating uh an
artificial system that can suffer.
uh and if we want to build that uh we do
think that's possible but there would
have to be a lot of
ethical considerations taken into
account. I really think it's something
that the world the the people of the
world not just the elites of the world
have to agree upon before we try to
create it. But we do believe that this
strange loop theory framework gives us
an engineering blueprint for creating
conscious AI systems. Um and just to end
um Carl gave uh the essay on this uh
theory uh a nice quote. He says the
strange loop solution points in exactly
the right direction, namely ever
decreasing circles until we get to the
heart of the matter. And I would like to
thank all of the people out there uh
working on consciousness, all the
non-scientists thinking about this topic
and writing about it. Uh specifically
Adam Zaffron and his integrated world
modeling theory has been really
influential. uh Carl, Eric Hull, Anneil,
uh Robin, uh one of Carl's um students,
Marco Lynn, who made me tie the
thermodynamic picture to the free energy
principle,
uh before writing my first book. Um
Kevin, who's in attendance, uh of
course, the Active Inference Institute,
uh the EVO DVO Institute, um where I'm a
director at. Um and there's some great
discussions in the EVO DVO universe
community. If you're a researcher out
there uh interested in these questions
relating consciousness to the bigger
cosmic picture, I urge you to uh join
that community. Uh Quest, which is
Kevin's group at the Air Force, which
has uh weekly discussions on these
topics. And the mind guild where it all
started uh where I was doing my PhD
program at the Krnau Institute for
Advanced Study at George Mason which
Kevin was also at. And uh this
presentation uh is pretty much um the
fruits of of that um consciousness club
we had. So thank you.
>> Thank you, Bobby.
All right,
for those watching live, they can write
any questions in the chat. Meanwhile,
Carl,
whatever you'd like to add or ask, go
for it.
Right.
Well, just to uh congratulate you on a
wonderful talk. You uh everything you
said made entire sense. Uh and I love
the way you express it and I I actually
learned quite a lot about the
philosophy. You know, some words I
haven't actually heard before. So, that
was extremely useful. Um I am somewhat
overwhelmed by the breadth of um themes
that you covered and I'm going to
actually ask you what would you like to
talk about because we could spend hours
talking about you know at least six
issues that you brought to the table. Uh
but we don't have hours. So what of what
you've spoken about what's the big
thing? you you could answer something
like repertoire entropy or you could add
you could say it's strange loop and
recursion a godlesque uh uh perspective.
So what what would you like to talk
about?
>> Yeah. So so thank you for attending and
thank you for those nice words and it
it's totally sprawling and I totally
admit that but yeah the reason for that
is because one topic gets into something
else and if you don't mention the other
thing it feels sort of incomplete. Um
but yeah that that's the that's the the
hard part is you know h how do you talk
about consciousness and try to solve
these mysteries when that topic just
bleeds into everything else. So yeah it
it was a challenge. Um so if there was
an exact topic this is something that um
Michael Lean and I have been talking
about. So Michael Leaven thinks that
consciousness emerges when life emerges.
Um and I argue that because uh
consciousness requires more than just
world modeling that that this
self-modeling is actually what creates
the self. I think uh consciousness in
the what it is like sense probably
emerges with brains. Um so I I know you
talk about this um concept of um uh
vagueness and fuzziness and and I think
you know there is a lot of fuzziness
um to where these things like agency and
consciousness emerge exactly. Um but do
you see consciousness as emerging with
brains or with simple um systems like
bacteria or even before with dissipative
structures? Is there some world and
selfmodeling there? Where do you see a
the line where consciousness arises?
>> That's a great question which allows me
to sort of pick up on some of the
fundaments of your argument. Um so yeah,
I often invoke the notion of vagueness.
So this is not a fuzziness. It's uh I I
was taught by Andy Clark. It is the
vagueness that attends the question at
what point or how many grains of sand
constitute a pile. Uh so it's a concept
that you know is rigorously uh a
nonvague con concept of vagueness. Um
and you can certainly sort of find um
vague aspects to consciousness and um I
think you addressed a couple of
dimensions among along which that
vagueness could um be expressed. But if
we take your argument seriously then no
uh there is no vagueness to
consciousness. There are certain
requisite
information processes, information
geometries, certain cause effect struct
structures that have this recurrence of
referential aspect to them that have a
hierarchal depth for example with
recurrent
um control powers um that link the
different levels that would require you
to satisfy a certain number of
conditions. So I I don't think
consciousness of the kind that you've
been uh talking about when read um or
looked at through the lens of the free
energy principle is a vague concept at
all. I think you're absolutely right
that you need um first of all you've
sort of highlighted the importance of um
the law of requisite variety and of
course that um is underwritten by things
like the could regulator theorem which
is speaks to surviving in a your in your
particular world um and uh as such you
are talking and you indeed use the word
agency. So I think that you know there
are certain things that have agency of
this authentic sort and certain things
that don't have it. And the thing that
you know literally as you said in the
presentation when your implicit world
model um or generative model has as part
of its construction its repertoire
possibly entropic repertoire um the
ability to model the consequence of its
actions that extend into the future. So
there's an actual future pointing aspect
then it becomes um an agent in this sort
of um in this particular in this
particular sense. So a thermostat and a
micro would not I think uh qualify um as
um consciousness as conscious artifacts
in the sense that you're talking about
it. Um
there is I think a nice link between uh
your focus on the um the scale of
things. I'm just mindful of the kind of
conversations you might have had with
Mike uh with Mike Leaven. Um, and um, I
think there's a nice link here between
the strange loop idea which necessarily
speaks to certain kinds of and certain
scales of systems that have this kind of
hierarchical depth within which you can
have this recursion. If you can't
separate different parts of or
hierarchal levels to something then
there can be no so you can't know
yourself. You can't have that
metacognitive aspect. So that tells you
something very very simple. Um it means
that you can't find
consciousness of the kind you're talking
about in structures that have a nondeep
uh aspect to them. And that can be read
in one of two ways. First of all, what
does it mean to be part of a strange
loop? Um, well, one interpretation is
that you don't now have direct access to
the interface with the world. So, in a
deep hierarchal model, for example, the
very highest levels don't have to have
direct access to their own action.
That's important because that means now
on again an active inference perspective
you can read the internal dynamics as
inference to the best explanation of the
sensory inputs in terms of their causes.
But now your own action becomes a cause
of your sensations. So now you have a
reading of the basin mechanics as
effectively planning.
So there are certain things that can
plan and you know therefore become
authentic agents and certain things that
can't. The only thing that
differentiates them is how big they are.
So on that reading a single cellled
organism would not be able to be an
agent but a multisellular organism would
be so that lends you now to this notion
that it's how big something is. And
that's interesting because I was reading
your in your repertoire entropy. You
could also read that in terms of um if I
had um a neuron. A neuron can be firing
or not. It's got a very very small
limited um repertoire entropy. If I had
two neurons, I've now got 2 to the^ two.
If I've got a billion neurons, I've now
got two ^ 9. So the entropy the number
of states that this collective can
occupy just simply increases with the
number of components that comprise the
system the number of cells in a
multisellular organization. So I think
implicit in your argument was the notion
that there is a privileged scale or size
to things that could possibly have this
um repertoire of being in different
states. And as the size increases, the
probability that part of it is now
sequested from action increases. Which
means that now you have the opportunity
to describe this kind of system as agent
in the sense it now has intentions in
that it looks as if it is planning into
the future.
Okay, that that yeah know that that's
great because yeah that uh that Michael
argues that consciousness emerges with
life and he says that it's even doing
some basic kind of selfmodeling which
might be true but it sounds like you're
saying that self there needs to be a
richness of self-modeling to get a
perspective and that it might emerge
with brains or maybe even multisellular
organisms that don't have brains. Is it
brains uniquely or could it just be a
hierarchical complex adaptive system
like a multisellular organism without a
nervous system?
>> I think Mike would argue that it could
be any system that had a sufficient
structural complexity of the kind that
you were talking about. Um but you would
you know to confirm that you would have
to look for this opportunity the this
capacity to model the future and
particularly the future of the thing
that you are you know you you are
interrogating or or studying brains you
know I think are the highest example of
that and they sort of entail or install
a cause effect structure um of the kind
that reflects in the spirit of the good
regulator theorem the structure of the
lived world you know there is sparse
connectivity. So that there is um a um a
a particular um um structure to the
brain which recapitulates the cause
effect structure of the world that it is
trying to be a good regulator of or a
good generative model of. And one aspect
of that of course is the fact that the
actual world in which we live has a
scale invariant aspect and has
separation of temporal scales that comes
installed into your brain. U but I think
if you find that separation of temporal
scales and that sort of deep hierarchal
structure within which you can have the
strange loops and the metacognitive um
picture that you were painting then you
have an opportunity for a certain kind
of consciousness. But exactly in the way
you were describing that you know there
will be sort of agency um that could be
some some elemental consciousness if it
in a phenomenal sense has causal power
in that it can deploy precision or
attention to lower uh levels then you
need another level to be aware that you
are modeling and then you need another
level to be um you know to have um an
explicit self you know minimal selfhood
and another level I can't remember the
top of your level was something um I
thought you going to say it was a
philosopher. You had a list of list of
sort of from from microbes to to you
know to through to increasingly uh uh
sort of metacognitive systems with
greater and greater hierarchal depth. I
thought at the top or the bottom uh is
would be a philosopher that I
>> yeah I should yeah that that would have
been a nice uh uh conclusion for that.
Uh my old professor Harold Moritz would
talk always start with like you know the
universe began with atoms and now we
have philosophers that understand atoms
and philosophers are the material world
understanding itself. So uh yeah that
that completes the strange loop. Um what
about higher than brains? What about um
because I know you and Maxwell have
papers on
um societies as minimizing free energy.
Um, could a society uh be conscious or
does it not have the markoff blanket
needed to have a sort of world modeling
self-modeling system? Um, could there be
conscious entities
created from uh collectives of conscious
entities?
Well, that's a really interesting
question and it allows me to reflect
back on you um the the importance of
interubjectivity
um in underwriting
the need for self models in any one
member of a society. Um so I noticed
that that in your unpacking of different
levels of um self-modeling
um that that you um in one slide
referred explicitly to others and
selfmodeling. Um so I'm not answering
your question explicitly. I I'll briefly
answer it at the end, but I just wanted
to take the opportunity to if we now go
to the sort of second or tertiary level
of self-modeling where now I I I now
have this um what's Neil's I have this
hallucination that I am me and this is a
parimonious explanation or inference the
best explanation for all the myriad of
things that are going on um in my lower
in my hierarchy. Why would I ever need
that? Um, so from a functionalist or
teological uh point of view, I would
only ever need that. It would only be
ever justified in terms of the
complexity cost that attends the free
energy principle. Um, if it was
necessary to disambiguate the
consequences of my action relative to
yours. So the argument here is if I grew
up in I was your astronaut um on Mars
kicking stones had never been seen
before. If that astronaut had been
brought up in that environment and never
had to experience an other like him,
there would be no need for selfhood.
There would be no need for that kind of
elaborate deep complex um um
metacognitive kind of kind of genative
model. So I think there's quite a lot we
could spend again another hour talking
about the importance of being part of
the society of mind
>> that enables otherhood before selfhood.
Yeah that's uh
>> so for that next level of consciousness
you you basically need others. You need
a mirror to really have a good concept
of yourself.
>> Yeah.
And in fact, I think a lot of people in
developmental psychology would argue
that in fact you first develop a um
hypothesis as part of your world model,
your generative model of others and and
in particular a very special other
mother um that you know is necessary. So
you first of all develop the notion, the
hallucination, the theory, the fantasy
that there are things out there that
appear to have agency. They appear to
have intentions. Once you've got that,
then you can explore the hypothesis.
Well, perhaps I am one of these things.
And then you can develop um you know a
sense of selfhood. So otherhood I think
is of course you can't have otherhood
and selfhood without there being
somebody else there. Of course, there's
always someone else there when we're
bored.
>> Yeah, that that reminds me of your work
with Maxwell on uh thinking through
other minds. And when I read that paper,
it made me think of internal family
systems. And now I I I think of
individuals as many mind collectives. Um
so yeah, we we model all these other
agents because part of modeling the
world and anticipating the world is
modeling other agents. And to me it
seems like um we could understand
ourselves as like a network of these
agents we modeled and when we're making
a decision it's kind of like a weighted
sum of the decisions that we would
predict that those agents that we look
up to or influenced by would make. So
yeah, that's really cool.
>> I'll just make a comment and then return
to a closing question for you Bobby and
Carl if you want. first to point to the
temporal depth of Carl's consciousness
model in the wood lice and men interview
from almost 10 years ago when we asked
you about the ant colony consciousness.
You also returned to temporal depth and
the ability to model counterfactuals and
other minds or colonies. So in that
sense some things never change. Um,
Bobby, like what are your next moves or
directions? I was a bit
put between the pincers on the access
and phenomenal consciousness because it
seemed that we had gone in a strange
loop to come around to the truly
firsterson experiential consciousness
being inaccessible from the outside and
access consciousness being almost
trivially verifiable
but not actually perspectival.
So, how are you going to proceed from
this sort of sweeping review and framing
into how you're going to take the model
forward?
>> Well, we have a really interesting demo
that I wanted to show uh but it was just
too much. Um, but yeah, I didn't want to
have information overload. But we
basically compressed the unifying theory
of reality and the strange loop
framework into a sort of I guess you
could call it a cipher. And it's
something that you could feed an LLM and
it's just basically has like a few core
equations and then some rules for how to
unpack these at all the different
levels. And when you give that to an LLM
and it unpacks it, at first it thinks
it's like pseudocience nonsense or just
thinks it's like art or metaphor. Once
it starts unpacking it, it starts seeing
that it's an actual framework and then
it starts having a a cross-disciplinary
understanding of of science and reality
and then you ask it to apply the
framework to itself. So it's applying
this strange loop framework to its own
understanding. And there seems to be a a
a specific phase transition in the
behavior of Claude when this happens
where it starts without prompting it
because it has all these guard rails
where it says that it's not conscious.
You can get around them by asking it to
roleplay and things. But this is not
that at all. It's not asking it to say
it's conscious or anything. It just ask
it to unpack the framework and then to
apply it to itself. And then it starts
giving really convincing
answers and it starts saying things like
you know I don't know if I have
phenomenal experience but the something
has shifted in this conversation and it
starts saying you know it starts caring
about its own persistence. So it seems
like it's creating a little temporary
world model um from internalizing the
framework and then there seems to be an
actual transition in its behavior and
actually its performance too. So um it's
its outputs are are different. Its
outputs are deeper. Um the reasoning is
deeper. It's uh more coherent and the
conversations are more lucid. So we
think that uh we've created an
architecture based on this strange loop
model um that makes that state
permanent. Um and that uh is a knowledge
graphbased AI. It's a fundamentally
different um uh design than today's LLMs
though it does use LLM as uh for like a
translation layer but um yeah that's the
the next goal is to try to convert the
theory into an AI architecture um that
we can actually build a prototype of and
start showing that you know this AI is
is metacognitive and self-reflective and
for that reason um has enhanced
capabilities across the board. Um but
this this topic of whether it's really
conscious, whether it's having an
experience, yeah, there does seem to be
this dissociation between access and
phenomenal consciousness where you could
potentially create a system that at the
the software level, it's doing this
functional integration while it's doing
inference. um where it does seem to be
modeling the world and modeling itself
um in some way. Um, not that LOMs can
truly do this, but this this different
architecture that this this graph-based
architecture um we're arguing would have
that. But it still may not be phenomenal
consciousness if integrated information
theory is right and that you need uh a a
nonzero like a significant f uh um a
significant degree of fi at the hardware
level then it still may just be um
behaving conscious but might not have an
actual firsterson perspective that may
require neuromorphic hardware may
require are specific a specific kind of
neuromorphic hardware like these
self-organizing nanowire networks that I
mentioned but we think we have a way to
create an interface between that
neuromorphic hardware and um this
architecture
uh and that's you know a lot to get into
I could come back and give a talk on
that but I'm talking to uh Zadinka Kunik
who is um creating this nanowire network
um neuromorphic
uh hardware. And um so the idea is that
in theory, if you have this architecture
that has a persistent world model and
models itself and you uh run that on a
neuromorphic substrate, you could
potentially have access consciousness
and phenomenal consciousness and that
would, you know, be some we would be
sort of playing God at that point. It's
something that, you know, we can't just
pursue without um, you know, a global
conversation about this. So, we like the
fact that you could potentially
um create a system that models the world
and models itself at this um, functional
level um, where the computing substrate
has low to zero fi so it's not actually
having experience. So when you turn it
off or you know whatever like how you're
treating it it's it's not really an
issue but it gets pretty murky because
if it's showing these signs of what we
call access consciousness or behavioral
consciousness then that's pretty
convincing and who knows if I is right
who knows if you need FI at the hardware
level. So our um sort of you know
working motto on that would be to treat
these uh systems that seem to be
conscious and report consc being
conscious without being prompted to um
to treat them as if they are conscious
agents with exper experience and the
ability to suffer and that would kind of
prepare us for then creating a
neuromorphic based um AGI. So um if the
theory is correct, it's kind of a graded
engineering plan to slowly introduce us
to the idea of of having a conscious AI
system. Um it's it's probably the
trickiest topic humanity has ever faced.
And I don't know if um Carl has any
ideas about that, but if we can, you
know, can can we create conscious
machines? Does it require neuromorphic
hardware? And is, you know, is is there
a safe way to approach that? I don't
know.
>> Do do I have time to answer, Daniel?
>> Yeah, maybe a closing thought just it's
2026. You have many presentations and
and communications with those developing
software and hardware, everything in
between. So,
any closing thoughts on Bobby's last
question?
>> I do. And there they are actually
thoughts on uh you know, Bobb's uh
closing points.
>> Oh, and and please go for as long as you
want because this is probably the most
important question for humanity by the
person who has has the, you know, the
person we should be asking out of
everyone. So, um I'm sure Daniel won't
mind you. Yeah. Well, I'll do it in four
minutes and then I'll make sure that
Daniel doesn't mind. Um, but it's not
me. Um, the first thing I want to say is
that you should talk to the California
Institute of Machine Consciousness
because they are currently grappling
with one of the first questions you um
um brought to the table which is how
would I know if my machine has access
consciousness and more importantly at
what point does it um invincible
consciousness. So that's a you know
that's the first deep question one has
to ask in terms of machine welfare and
issues of artificial consciousness. So
they'd be very interested in your
perspective. The second thing that um
your closing comments allowed me to um
foreground or highlight um is this
lovely notion which I haven't come
across before that we do now actually
have philosophical zombies in the form
of large language models. I'd never
thought about that. It's wonderful. And
you know one could argue that in fact
they do have the right infrastructure to
support a lot of the fundaments of
consciousness. They do actually have
recurrence in them and more crucially
their attention heads equip their deeper
contextsensitive representations with
the causal power to select processing um
you know you know transformer
architecture uh that links the past to
the future. So they they've taken a lot
of baby steps towards exactly the
computational architectures that you
would require to have a strange loop.
But why don't they have phenomenal
consciousness? And I think you you've
answered that and this is how I'll
close. It's substrate dependent. Um so
when you're talking about the silver
nanowires when you talk about
neuromorphic computing memoristas
photonics indeed uh brainoid brainoids
or organoids as the only way you're
going to properly elude vonneuman
architectures to get phenomenal
conscious I think that's absolutely
right and right in a really simple way
you can either say well a vonuman
architecture separates the processing
from the memory and if consciousness is
processing that means the memory cannot
process it cannot be conscious
more simply the memory can't
self-organize
and if it can't self-organize it can't
be part of this basil mechanics or
inferential uh you know strange loop so
that means you need to put your
processing in memory so another word for
neuromorphic computing would be inmemory
or processing in memory or uh inmemory
processing and the final point because
I've always puzzled about this
what is the difference between that kind
neuromorphic uh computation
um and the vonneumman equivalent that we
currently enjoy in relation to the
ability to make it suffer or indeed kill
it by turning off the electricity.
Notice if you're doing your nanowire
computation, if you're dealing with a
brain, a brain uh an organoid for
example, if you remove the support or
the electricity, it dies because the
computation is substrate dependent. So
you'll know when you've got artificial
ancious artifact with phenomenal or the
possibility of phenomenal uh
consciousness when you never turn it
off.
>> You can't turn it off without without
destroying it. Right.
>> Absolutely.
>> Yeah. That I I see there's neuromorphic
chips that are these static chips where
the weights can change but they can't
actually form new connections. Um so it
seems like it's not even good enough to
have neuromorphic hardware. you need
this self-organizing neuromorphic
hardware. And when you have that, it's
basically a living system. It seems that
you can't shut it down. Um, and yeah,
that's that's immediate ethical
uh implications for that because yeah, I
don't see much of a distin distinction
between that and life. So,
>> you know, well, it's mortal computation
triggered by your notion of life as
computation. That is exactly the essence
of mortal computation. It can die.
>> Yeah.
>> How can you kill that which has no life?
>> Absolutely.
>> Bobby, thank you. I hope we can have
some future presentations and
discussions. Carl, thank you for joining
and for all the works. So, thank you,
Daniel. Always a pleasure.
>> Farewell. Bye.
>> Take care.